<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Dan Ubilla]]></title>
  <link href="http://danubilla.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://danubilla.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-01T22:41:55-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://danubilla.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dan Ubilla]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[dan.ubilla@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ultramarathon Man]]></title>
    <link href="http://danubilla.com/blog/books/ultramarathon-man.html"/>
    <updated>2009-06-01T01:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://danubilla.com/blog/books/ultramarathon-man</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img aligncenter /images/www/ultramarathonman.jpg 158 250 &lsquo;ultramarathon man&rsquo; &lsquo;Ultramarathon Man&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>A few weeks ago, I finished up &ldquo;Ultramarathon Man&rdquo; by Dean Karnazes.  It&rsquo;s an excellent memoir by a regular guy who picked up and fell in love with beating the hell out of his body through endurance running.  I highly recommend it to anyone who&rsquo;s looking for inspiration for their workouts.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here are a few quotes I jotted down from the book.</p>

<p>&ldquo;If it felt good,&rdquo; [my coach] said, squinting like Clint Eastwood, &ldquo;you didn&rsquo;t push hard enough.  It&rsquo;s supposed to hurt like hell.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Go out there and run to the best of your ability,&rdquo; he replied.  &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t run with your legs.  Run with your heart.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;This was an exploration into the possibilities of self.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Throeau once said that a man&rsquo;s riches are based on what he can do without.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Most dreams die a slow death.  They&rsquo;re conceived in a moment of passion, with the prospect of endless possibility, but often languish and are not pursued with the same heartfelt intensity as when first born.  Slowly, subtly, a dream becomes elusive and ephemeral.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;What [the supporters] cared about was that a person had taken the time to train, and sacrifice, and dedicate himself wholeheartedly to the pursuit of a dream.  It was a powerful message; I was just the host.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Yes, I had failed &ndash; but it had actually been a sepctacular failure, gloriously disintegrating every aspect of my body and soul until I literally fell over in the dirt.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;People think I&rsquo;m crazy to put myself through such torture, though I would argue otherwise.  Somewhere along the line we seem to have confused comfort with happiness.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;You only live once, but if you work it right, once is enough.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
