<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ramblings | Dan Ubilla]]></title>
  <link href="http://danubilla.com/blog/categories/ramblings/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://danubilla.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-08T21:33:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://danubilla.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dan Ubilla]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[dan.ubilla@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going Back]]></title>
    <link href="http://danubilla.com/blog/ramblings/going-back.html"/>
    <updated>2009-07-26T16:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://danubilla.com/blog/ramblings/going-back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img aligncenter size-full wp-image-96 /images/www/shedeservesit.jpg 400 268 &lsquo;She Deserves It&rsquo; &lsquo;She Deserves It&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>The ambiguity of the narrator on this Post Secret really struck a chord.  The possibilities of all three roles are endless and striking.  Why did the male lead leave?  What is the female lead doing in the meanwhile?  We do know the male character is coming back; it&rsquo;s simply a matter of when.  How is the narrator related to either of the main characters?  And what to make of the starry, dreamy night sky backdrop?</p>

<p>It works because the reader has enough information to create their own version of the story.  What&rsquo;s your version?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://danubilla.com/blog/ramblings/the-great-experiment.html"/>
    <updated>2009-03-02T00:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://danubilla.com/blog/ramblings/the-great-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow is the first day of the work month which normally means two big purchases: my Commuter Rail pass and my T/Bus pass.  For the first time since I&rsquo;ve come to this fair city, the $59 T pass is getting left out.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>A two-way T trip runs $2.50, so I would have to ride the T 24 times to be in the red, or black, or in the loss column on this endeavor.  That means a trip a day, which is normally the case, except now I walk the 12 minutes to the Porter Station instead of the 5 minutes to the Davis stop.  Amazingly, this gives me two extra minutes in the morning before I have to leave the door since I don&rsquo;t have to catch the T at Davis, I&rsquo;m just jumping on the commuter train at Porter.  And, if I do happen to leave a little late, I can still make it to the Porter station on time if I run a block for every minute that I&rsquo;m late (math on that exact ratio is still in testing).</p>

<p>Regardless, I&rsquo;m generally happy running the extra block or two so long as I&rsquo;m able to cue up a BS Report before I walk out the door.</p>

<p>Back to the experiment, I think I can cut my T trips down to 16 a month without breaking a sweat, which means a cool $20 in my pocket every month.  Chances are I&rsquo;ll try and save this, but let&rsquo;s take a look at what $20 can go to:</p>

<p>$20 = 1.5 meals out with friends = 1 rack of Busch Light</p>

<p>Exciting!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alive!]]></title>
    <link href="http://danubilla.com/blog/ramblings/alive.html"/>
    <updated>2009-03-01T17:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://danubilla.com/blog/ramblings/alive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One, two&hellip;</p>

<p>One, two, three, four.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
